java se : applicatif standard. juste créer des applis
java ee : réduit le temps de code. sécuriser le code. outils de sécurisation. maintenance : gestion des bugs (maintenance corrective), rajouter des fonctionnalités (maintenance évolutive). code à maintenir. utilisation à travers le web. 

entreprise -> logique métier : partie/contrainte spécifique à chaque applications.

client ---web---> Serveur d'application (Tomcat) <---- BDD (MySQL)
MVC : Model View Controler
JPA : Java Persistence API : gère la persistance des objets.
Java Standard : pas de persistance. mémoire limité.
En entreprise, on ne va pas recréer des clients tous les jours par exemple -> assurer la persistance. persistence lié à la BDD

exo : Tableau abcdef, inverser les tableaux

pseudo code : code permettant le bon fonctionnement entre les machines 32 et 64 bits. code "intermédiaire".

portable = multiplateforme

l'architecture java est modulaire -> plus sécurisé.

Augmenter la productivité du développeur : outils de développement (briques réutilisables, templates)

Multitier : Client/Serveur avec plusieurs 'tiers' offrant des fonctions différentes. 

A Java EE multitiered application is generally composed of :
Client-tier components : run on the client machine
Web-tier components : run on the Java EE server
Business-tier components : run on the Java EE server
Enterprise Information System : run on the EIS server

Plus facile a gérer, a developper et à maintenir

JavaServer Faces : ergonomie et présentation des pages internet.

Enterprise Beans (EJB) : JavaBeans de la parte Business Tier.
Database -> gestion de la JPA (Persistence)

Applet : Application qui s'éxécute sur la machine. Petite application sans 'main'. impossible de voir le code d'une applet.
l'applet s'éxécute dans un 'bac à sable' (sandbox).

Application clients and applets 
	 Run on the client
Servlet, JSF and JSP technology components 
	 Web components, run on the server
Enterprise JavaBeans components
	 Business components, run on the server

Containers : Va servir le role d'interface/intermédiaire entre le composant de haut niveau et la machine de bas niveau

Les containers vont assurer la sécurité de la 'transaction'
Remote connectivity

Container pour chacun des tiers (Container pour le business tier)

Container types :
- Java EE Server :
	The runtime portion of a Java EE product
	Provides EJB and Web containers
- Enterprise JavaBeans container :
	Manages the execution of EJBs
- Web container :
	Manages the execution of web pages and servlets

=/= entre internet et web : internet, c'est plus le réseau, l'infrastructure. web, c'est le contenu.

Composant > Container > Resultat
Permet l'éxécution d'un composant

Serveurs EJB : JBoss, Oracle, GlassFish, IBMWebSphere

Java Persistence 2.0 (JSR 317) :
Java standards-based solution for persistence
Use an object/relational mapping approach
Mapping : mettre des objets dans une bdd relationnel.

Enterprise JavaBeans 3.1 (JSR 318) :
Component that encapsulates the business logic
Provide :
	Transaction processing
	Concurrency control
	Remote procedure calls
	Exposing business methods as Web Services

JavaServer Faces 2.0 (JSR 314) :
A Component Based Framework for Web
Support :
	Input validation
	Event handling
	Data conversion
	Page navigation configuration

Bean Validation (JSR 303) :
Define a meta-data model and API for JavaBean validation based on annotations
New in Java EE 6

Brique de base dans la logique métier.

JCP : Java Community Process : cycle de validation des maj des standards java. S'assure de la stabilité et de la compatibilité des standards. Communauté Java
JSR : Java Specification Request : Proposition de standard crée par la JCP, qui peut être rejeté ou validé por devenir un composant java

__________________________________________________________________

admin
ceECpJ6dM&Hr

__________________________________________________________________

RIA : Rich Interface Architecture
Client Rich : une partie de l'application est partagé au client
Client Léger : juste une app web par exemple
Java Message Server : JMS
JavaBeans : il fonctionne un peu comme un cerveau : centre de fonctionnement, propose divers services, dont le session beans

Session Beans : On peut avoir JPA (Java Persistence API), lié à la JDBC (Java Database Connection)
JTA : Java Transaction API
RMI / JNDI : Remote Method Invocation / Java Naming Domain Interface
Ressemble un peu à l'Active Directory, identifier chacun des objets dans le système, on va pouvoir l'utiliser comme ça
JMS : Java Message Server
Socket : interface de connection
Technologies qui se complètent

Les versions avant la 3.0 étaient trop compliqués.
mtn : plus simplifiés, moins de classes, moins de tâches, moins de config. Ajout d'annotations, génériques, JPA...

The Java Persistence API originated as part of the work of the EJB specification.  
Since version 2.0, JPA is defined in a separate JSR.
JPA was so easy and powerful than community asked to be able to use it independently of the EJBs.
Now, end-users do not need an EJB container or a Java EE application server in order to run applications that use this persistence API (remember last year ?)

Java EE 6 introduce the version 3.1
This version tends to more simplification :
EJB Interfaces become optional in specific cases
EJB Lite specification for embedded containers
Asynchronous invocation
Further other simplifications…
Simplification d'interface
Invocation asynchrone
-> invocation sans attente
il peut invoquer la methode et faire autre chose en mm temps

Session Bean : quelque chose (services) qui va s'executer du coté serveur dont le but est d'offrir des services au client.

Service d'authentification (équivalent de ldap), recherche des éléments

la session bean fonctionne comme une facade, c'est l'interlocuteur.
facade : partie visible par le client
subsystem : fonction interne de la session pas visible par le client.

Session bean déployé dans un serveur -> app bureau / app web


Interface :
pour pouvoir créer un session bean; il faut des classes prédéfinies.
The interface contains all services provided by the Session Bean as methods
We have a simple method returning a String :
	@Remote
	public interface HelloService {
		public String sayHello();
	}

Implémentation :
Annotations transform this class into a Session Bean
	@Stateless
	public class HelloServiceBean implements HelloService{
    		public String sayHello(){
        	return "Hello World";
    		}
	}

implements -> héritage seulemenet pour les interfaces
extends n'accepete qu'un seul élément, qu'une seule classe.

interface : liste de méthode vide dans aucun contenu, prototype des méthodes. implémente uniquement des comportements
classe : partie structure plus un comportement

spécification unique, comportement multiple

Client connection :
The application server hosts the Session Bean
The client needs the JNDI context to connect to the server. It could be put either :
	In a properties file
	Directly in the code
The client also needs the Session Bean interface, to know which methods are available

interface -> ouvre session -> implémenter méthodes -> ouvrir la session via la connection -> besoin des services JNDI.

Initialize JNDI context with a jndi.properties file
Retrieve the Session Bean with a lookup()
Then it's possible to call methods from the Bean :
	Context context = new InitialContext();
	HelloService helloService = (HelloService) context.lookup			("java:global/HelloEJB/HelloServiceBean!				com.supinfo.ejbdemo.service.HelloService");
	System.out.println(hello.sayHello());
The Session Bean will send you a message !


But… what is this long string as parameter of the lookup method ? You know, the :
java:global/HelloEJB/HelloServiceBean!com.supinfo.ejbdemo.service.HelloService

It is the JNDI name of our EJB !
Each EJB is registered in JNDI with a specific name

The default pattern of JNDI names is :
java:global[/<applicationName>]/<moduleName>/<beanName>!<interfaceName>

applicationName (facultative): Name of the application in which is packaged the EJB. By default, the name of the EAR archive. 

moduleName: Name of the module in which is packaged the EJB. By default, the name of the jar or the war.

beanName: Bean name. By default, the name of the implementation class.

interfaceName: FQDN of the EJB Interface. If the EJB doesn’t have Interface, use the FQDN of the implementation class.


Do we need to access remotely to the Session Bean?
“Remote” or “Local” access

Do we need a processing in several steps? 
“Stateless” or “Stateful” mode

Chacun va implémenter à sa manière
ex : se déplacer. oiseau -> vole, chien -> cours, etc

Session Bean : Local / Remote

Statefull/Stateless : passer par toutes les étapes ou non
Stateless : en une seule étape

Entity : lien entre l'application et la base de données

POJO = Plain Old Java Object : Classe Java classique (=/= de Java standard, on est en JEE)
exemple : 
	public class Contact implements Serializable {

		// my properties
		private int id;
		private String name;
		private String firstname;

		// ... setters and getters ...
	}
… embellished with JPA annotations : ex : @Entity, @Id, @Override...

Top Link : Récupère les informations, faire le lien objet / Base de données.

EM : Entity Manager : Fait toutes les manipulations possible sur les entités.
	// The Entity Manager em inserts the Country object into the database via the persist method
	public Country addCountry(Country c) {
    		em.persist(c);
    		return c;
	}
Some common operations :
	void persist(Object entity)‏
	<T> T merge(T entity)‏
	void remove(Object entity)‏
	<T> T find(Class<T> entityClass, Object primaryKey) 

Primary Key : Valeur unique permettant d'identifier un objet
Foreign Key : clé primaire d'une autre part qui lie une table à une autre

proxy : sert de filtre aux requetes http

Un Session Bean doit posséder
- une interface : pour pouvoir y accéder. Nécessaire pour un client, mais pas vraiment pour un accès local
- une implémentation

EJB Lite : version allégée de EJB
Local Session Beans
Injection
Transactions
Mais pas de Remote Session ou de Message Driven.

EJB 3.1 also provide a new annotation: @Asynchronous
Provide a way to execute an EJB method asynchronously

communication asynchrone : pas besoin d'attendre la fin d'un traitement pour reprendre une tâche.

@Asynchronous annotation can be used on classes or methods
To choose if all the methods from the EJB must be asynchronous or just some of them
Future interface defines the following methods :
cancel(boolean)
Attempts to cancel execution of this task
get()
Waits for the computation to complete, and then retrieves its result
isCancelled()
Returns true if this task was cancelled before it completed normally
isDone()
Returns true if this task completed



__________________________________________________________________

Advanced JPA :

JPA supports inheritance dependencies

@Inheritance annotation supports 3 different strategies :
SINGLE_TABLE
TABLE_PER_CLASS
JOINED

SINGLE_TABLE Strategy
All data are in the same table
@DiscriminatorColumn : 
One column is used as discriminator 
@DiscriminatorValue : 
Each subclass have to precise the discriminator value used
Many columns unused

jointures

Criteria API : Attempt to “simplify” dynamic query creation

We commonly use four classes in Criteria API :

CriteriaBuilder
Used to create CriteriaQuery objects and construct Predicate objects

CriteriaQuery
Defines functionality that is specific to top-level queries (select, where, orderBy, …)

Predicate
A simple or compound predicate: a conjunction or disjunction of restrictions

Root
A root type in the from clause (reference entity)

queryBuffer : buffer dans lequel on écrit la requete


This API is used to create a Metamodel of each managed entities

For each entity class, a Metamodel class is created

What is a Metamodel class ?
A class with the same name than an entity with a trailing underscore
With attributes that correspond to the properties of the entity class
@Static Metamodel(Sale.class)
public class Sale_ {
	public static volatile SingularAttribute<Sale, Long> id;
	public static volatile SingularAttribute<Sale, Date> date;
	public static volatile SingularAttribute<Sale, Product> product;
}

volatile : stocké en mémoire, se bar après


___________________________________________________________________

JMS (Java Message Server)

Utilisé lorsque des informations doit être echangés entre 2 applications ou plusieurs applications.
Principe des newsletter : inscription. A chaque fois que quelque chose est publié -> contact aux abonnés

Systeme asynchrone

JMS require different actors :
A provider, which stores messages and sends them to consumers (qui envoie)
A producer, which sends messages (qui transfere)
One or several consumers, which receives messages (qui reçoit)

A destination could be compared to a mailbox
The producer creates a message for a specific destination
The provider stores the message until the consumer receives it

With GlassFish, we can create Queues and Topics directly inside the administration console 

blocking : attendre un message, ne rien faire
non-blocking : vous allez eécouter, il y a un listener, pas bloqué par l'attente du message.

There are three different types of messages :
TextMessage to send simple text
ObjectMessage for a serialized object
MapMessage contains a map with strings as keys and objects as values

Message Driven Bean

A Message Driven Bean is a specific component for receiving messages
Annotation used is @MessageDriven
Destination name and type are declared in the annotation
Implements javax.jms.MessageListener
Method onMessage(Message m)
Called at the moment of receipt

There are 2 message distribution modes:
Queue and Topic

Destination : équivalent à un abonnement : queue ou topic
Queue : = mail
Topic : = newsletter

___________________________________________________________________


A Web Service is a software system that allows communication between two electronic devices over the web

REST : En fonction de l'url et de la méthode , renvoie des resultats, ajoute/supprime des trucs dans bdd


SOAP means Simple Object Access Protocol
RPC protocol based on XML
Allow messages transmission between two remote object
Remote Procedure Call !
Usually used with HTTP but can be used with other protocols (SMTP, …)

SOAP messages are composed of two parts :
A Header (optional)
A Body

Both parts are inside a SOAP Envelope

How a client can know about procedure he can call ?
Thanks to WSDL !

Web Services Description Language is an XML format for describing network services as a set of endpoints operating on messages containing either document-oriented or procedure-oriented information

It thus serves a roughly similar purpose as a Method signature in a programming language

JAX-WS is an API that can be used :
In server side to define Web Services
In client side to consume Web Services

SOAP Web Services are interoperable !
So you can use JAX-WS to consume a Web Service develop in another technology

JAX-WS API is very easy :
Just need to write the desired service…
… enhanced by annotations ! (again)

No need to handle how the SOAP response will be written
Just concentrate on the business rules !

To define a Web Service, just use the @WebService annotation 

But how to generate the WSDL file based on that services ?

JAX-WS do it for you !

Available at that URL : 

http://<host>/<context-path>/<service-name>?WSDL

Look at the WSDL file of our CircleFunctions Web Service !

marshal/unmarshal

payload : charge, transmission.

JAX-WS support other annotations to customize and control even more the result of the Web Service : 
@WebResult
@SOAPBinding
@BindingType
Etc…

We have seen how to create a Web Service with JAX-WS
But how to consume it from another application ?
JAX-WS can be used to do that too !

Remember, JAX-WS can be used to consume all SOAP Web Services, whatever the language used to develop them !

All what you need is :
The WSDL location
The JAX-WS libraries

The term comes from Roy Fielding’s doctoral dissertation
REpresentational State Transfer

He defines a RESTful system with the following constraints :
It must be a client-server system
It has to be stateless
It has to support a caching system
It has to be uniformly accessible
It has to be layered (support scalability)

The static web is RESTful by default, not the dynamic one

SOAP est un standard contrairement à REST, mais REST est plus facile à utiliser.

URI : Uniform Ressource Identify. l'url est un uri. courte chaîne de caractères identifiant une ressource sur un réseau


The method GET is used to RETRIEVE resources
For instance, a GET request to the URI /students return all the students

The method POST is used to CREATE resources

The method PUT is used to UPDATE resources

The method DELETE is used to DELETE resources

JAXB for Java Architecture for XML Binding
Allow to map Java classes to XML representations
Two main features are :
Marshal Java objects into XML
Unmarshal XML into Java objects

Very useful for Web Services !





















